<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The consolation of the soule being an assurance of the forgiuenesse of sinnes, with the most notable promises of God conteined in holy Scripture, both in the olde and newe Testament: briefly expounded and applied, as hereafter followeth. With certaine examples woorth the bearing in minde, touching the great mercies of God, towards poore, and miserable sinners. ... Made by Iohn Chassanion, and englished by H. S. of Greyes Inne. Gent.</title>
            <title>Consolation de l'âme sur l'asseurance de la remission des pechez. English.</title>
            <author>Chassanion, Jean de, 1531-1598.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18521</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118621</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853828</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853828</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19226</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18521)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19226)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 416:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The consolation of the soule being an assurance of the forgiuenesse of sinnes, with the most notable promises of God conteined in holy Scripture, both in the olde and newe Testament: briefly expounded and applied, as hereafter followeth. With certaine examples woorth the bearing in minde, touching the great mercies of God, towards poore, and miserable sinners. ... Made by Iohn Chassanion, and englished by H. S. of Greyes Inne. Gent.</title>
                  <title>Consolation de l'âme sur l'asseurance de la remission des pechez. English.</title>
                  <author>Chassanion, Jean de, 1531-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[94] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Orwin] for Symon Waterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1590?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of Jean Chassagnon's: La consolation de l'âme sur l'asseurance de la remission des pechez.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A C-G (-G8).</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Forgiveness of sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19226:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19226:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Conſolation of the Soule, being an aſſurance of <hi>the forgiueneſse of ſinnes, with the moſt</hi> notable promiſes of God conteined in holy Scripture, both in the olde and newe Teſtament: briefly expounded and applied, as hereafter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With certaine examples woorth the bearing in minde, touching the great mercies of God, towards poore, and miſerable ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>When I am troden vnder foote, thy mercies doth lift me vp againe. <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Made by <hi>Iohn Chaſsanion,</hi> and engli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by H.S. of Greyes Inne. Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London for</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Waterſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19226:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19226:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the faithfull of the <hi>refourmed Church of Metz</hi> grace, and peace through <hi>Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EING it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed GOD (deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren) to make mee an Inſtrument, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to declare his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde vnto you, I thought it very need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to preſent this little Booke, wherein I entend not to teach any newe matter, but to put you in mind of your ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which you haue of long tyme knowne, and doe daily heare, to the end, it may be the better rooted in your hearts. And ſo much the rather, ſeeing by this you haue at all tymes ſuch meanes to reioyce, and comfort your ſelues in God, whereby we may gather very many good inſtructions in Gods ſchoole, if we bee certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of his grace, and indeuour our
<pb facs="tcp:19226:3"/> ſelues, both to obey him, and to amend that, we finde to be amiſſe in vs. Alſo we ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually lift vp our harts towards him, that we may be partakers of his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, &amp; bountifulneſſe, the very ground of our ſaluation. After which maner, doe the children of God truely exerciſe them ſelues in meditation, &amp; looke throughly into the vnſpeakable goodneſſe of him, by whome they are ſaued through Ieſus Chriſt, euen with an vndefiled thought and hope. Alſo it is requiſite, that there bee a true amendment of life, agreeable both to the ſeruice, obedience, &amp; honor, which we owe vnto him, and to cal vpon him vnfaynedly. All which are the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt points, comprehended in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and here ſummarily ſpoken of, for the confirmation of our faith, and hope: the full aſſurance wherof is as it were the foundation of all others, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting in the certaine perſwaſion, which we ought to haue of the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes, to which end alſo principally the preaching of the Goſpell doth attende: by reaſon whereof S. Paule calleth it, the miniſtrie of reconciliation. How happeneth it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the Cleargie men in our companie
<pb facs="tcp:19226:3"/> by an holie, and religious cuſtome, euery Sonday in morning prayers, declare the grace of God, that is to ſay, the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes to all true penitent Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, beeing neceſſarie for euery one to knowe? Certainly, principally for this cauſe, that all may bee perſwaded, that their offences bee forgiuen them before God: and that they bee reconciled vnto him, and receiued into his grace, what i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquitie ſoeuer they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted. And this certaine perſwaſion ought to be ſtedfaſt, and deepely rooted in our hearts, chiefly in the tyme of Calamities, and great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, whereunto the children of God are continually ſubiect, hauing the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and peruerſe worlde their enemie, which will neuer agree with them, being ſet forward, and inflamed by him, which from the beginning is a murtherer, and an aduerſarie to all mankinde: and neuer leaueth in reſt thoſe, that giue themſelues to the true ſeruice of their god, but doth procure vnto them all hinderances and lets, that he can, and continually aſſaults them with mortall warres, compaſsing them with euilles rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about, &amp; ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppreſsing them, when they doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
<pb facs="tcp:19226:4"/> tyme. It may ſeeme then, that for a tyme God doth giue them ouer, and that he is very angrie with them, and that he would vndo them, and that they be loſt: but they hauing this ful knowledge, that by his infinite bountie and clemencie, he doth receiue them into his mercie, and quiet orders: See how they are reuiued, and comforted, and their conſciences in reſt. And to this end, is the worde of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation giuen vnto them, by the which God doth promiſe to be mercifull vnto them: If then ſuch a ſimple promiſe bee ſufficient to make them certaine of his loue towards them; how much more will it be, when al other promiſes doe abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d? It is therefore for this cauſe, that I haue gathered here a certain number of moſt ſinguler notes of the holie Scripture, which conſequently are added, &amp; which are taken from one, and the ſelfe ſame ſpring, which ſhalbe like towers, &amp; ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g places moſt high to defend vs againſt the terrible and perilous aſſaults of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and to put off from vs, all increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and miſtruſt. That, which I preſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, welbeloued brethren, I dedicate it to witneſſe the good affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that God
<pb facs="tcp:19226:4"/> hath giuen me towards you, wiſhing that more and more you may be ſtedfaſt, and conformable in the faith, and certaintie of the fatherly goodwill of our God. We cannot but alwaies hope well of ſuch a gentle and gracious father, which haue looked on vs a long tyme, with his owne eyes, and hath viſited vs, as his owne, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the true &amp; happy light of his word, and by excellent Shepeheards (of which ſome are already receiued into perpetual reſt with the Lord: others ſerue him yet happely in other places) he hath eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the miniſtrie of his Goſpell among you, which you inioye at this preſent, by his ineſtimable bountie: although the bluſtringes of the tempeſtes lately paſt, haue brought into many and diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſome ſtraunge troubles and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. This good God neuertheleſſe, hath alwaies care to preſerue you in ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, that you haue continuall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to giue him thanks, the very tokens, and witneſſes of your faith, which may appeare in that, that you neede not gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly to ſeeke for the nouriſhment of your ſoules three long myles, farre from your houſes, neither in painfull and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull
<pb facs="tcp:19226:5"/> waies. Continue alwaies therfore in this zeale, for the glory of God, and in the confidence of his goodwill, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie towards you vnto the ende. I deſire thoſe which bee ſlouthfull to come into the paſture of the Lord, to conſider what he ſayth in this place, when he ſayth: <hi>that his ſheepe follow him and doe heare his voyce.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> And what he ſayth in an other place: <hi>He which is of God heareth Gods worde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> I doe warne them therefore with my brothers and fellowes, to be moſt affected in it, &amp; not to bee giuen ſo much to the loue of the world, &amp; to their vanities: to the end that they maye not depriue themſelues before they be aware, from the celeſtiall goods and riches which are euerlaſting. Deare brethren, I pray to our God &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that in houlding you alwaies vnder the ſhadowe of his winges, he may cauſe you to profite more and more in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledge, and continually to fortifie you in his ſeruice, and to repleniſh you withal the gifts of his holy Spirite, to his honor and glory, &amp; to your conſolation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble and affected brother in the Lord.</hi> Iohn Chaſſanion.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19226:5"/>
            <head>¶ The Conſolation of the <hi>Soule, being an aſſurance of the</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſinnes, with the moſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble promiſes of GOD conteyned in the holy Scripture, as well in the old, as new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, briefly expounded, and applied vnto the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F hee to whome the forgiuenes of ſinne is giuen, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome ſinne is put away, bee happie, as it is ſayd in the xxxij. Pſalme: <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie is the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to whom God imputeth no ſinne.</hi> He nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to doubt, but on the contrary parte he is vnhappie, which is tyed and bound in ſinne, he muſt looke for none other thing but for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation, and ruyne onely. Be it for a time he liues in eaſe, &amp; takes his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and altogether giues himſelfe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: though he be increaſed with honor, and euery bodie doe loue and cheare him: yet he
<pb facs="tcp:19226:6"/> is neuertheleſſe vnhappie, if he be not ſet at libertie by grace, and forgiueneſſe of his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities: for ſinne is a burthen ſo hard, &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, that no man is able to beare it, pulling downe euery one that is laden with it: from whence it appeareth, that ſome do bowe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, and falles into ruine, and brings them ſelues into diſpayre: as it happened to Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das. Other being oppreſſed in ſuch ſort, that they cannot ſcant receiue any comfort and reſt. I haue ſeene a man, which hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, as himſelfe doth confeſſe, ſome great and notorious faults, was ſo abated &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in his ſpirite by the memorie of them, that he did reſemble a poore man, which was indepted, and condemned to a greeuous ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance and ſhamefull death, he did alwaies grone and ſigh with the trouble and paine of his Soule, feeling himſelfe ſo guiltie, and doubting of the mercies of God, for the inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of his ſinnes: in ſuch ſort, that he made not any account to eate any meate, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take any nouriſhment if hee had not beene carefully mooued thereunto by thoſe which did keepe him companie: his heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo oppreſſed with dolor, that ſometimes he wiſhed that his bodie might bee puniſhed with Iuſtice, and that hee might ſuffer ſome
<pb facs="tcp:19226:6"/> greeuous paine to make his torment leſſe: which hee thought, hee had deſerued in his ſoule: Sometimes in his anguiſh, he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to bee comforted, and receiued into the Church by publicke pennance, but he was a ſtraunger, and did but paſſe away. I haue ſeene an other, which hauing a long time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed the true knowledge of God: yet at the laſt had ſuch remorſe of conſcience, which did gnawe his heart ſo, that he was conſtrayned to lye as ſicke, and out of breath. See there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how horrible &amp; heauie ſinne is of it ſelfe, from which whoſoeuer is lightned, though he bee neuer ſo poore, miſerable, and diſpiſed of the world, or otherwiſe afflicted, he is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe an happie man. The blinde man of this world doth not eſteeme nor iudge of theſe things otherwiſe then by apparance of deceiptfull vanities, and not in trueth, as it appeareth daylie: but the ſpirite of GOD doth teach the godly otherwiſe, as it is afore ſayd. That man is then very happy, that fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the grace of God to be ſuch, as to haue his ſinne forgiuen him: for then his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience is in peace and reſt, and he feareth not to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, neither hath he the iudgements of God in horror, but aſſureth himſelfe of his fauour, and bountifulneſſe, which God is to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:19226:7"/> the greateſt, that a man can receiue in this mortall world. Among the Saraſines, thoſe which haue not conſidered of thinges very narrowlie, haue yet well knowne, that it was a precious treaſure not to bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by any committed forfeite: of which the moſt wittie and ſufficient among them haue made a treatiſe, which he calleth the quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Soule: but altogether ignorant of this poynt of the free forgiuenes of ſinne, as all other Philoſophers, not eſteming any other reſt of conſcience, but in vertue and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie of life, which is but an imagination of no value before God: for this man is like vnto him, which buildeth without foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and would make a ſhew of that thing which is not. For to come then vnto ſuch bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to inioye ſo happie felicitie, wee muſt knowe, that GOD to whom we muſt giue an accompt, is gentle and mercifull, to whom wee ought to haue all our refuge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing certaine, that he will be quiet and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full towards vs: neither imputing our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, but will forgiue vs them freely.</p>
            <p>Then as the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ſicke and lingering de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed haue more neede of remedies for to be helped, and eaſed of their griefe and paine: likewiſe alſo the moſt troubled ſoules, which
<pb facs="tcp:19226:7"/> are tormented with ſorrowe, and anguiſh by feeling, and acknowledging their greate ſinnes, dreading the anger and moſt feareful iudgement of God, haue more neede of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and greater aſſurances of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, wherevpon their hope ſhould be totally founded and rooted. Who although ſome times they be debaſed by diuers temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, yet by the mercies of their God, they neuer fall into any diſſolation or confuſion by diſpaire: although it happen, that the moſt forwarde in Religion and in the feare of God, haue to ſuſteine many temptations of Sathan, who doth often giue them hotte ſkirmiſhes, and ſhooteth againſt them his poyſoned and mortall arrowes, for to abate their faith, and to caſt them into euerlaſting diſtruction, if it were poſſible for them ſo to fall, and if they ſome times ſeeme to doubt, being trobled by diſtruſt, and fearefulnes, yet it neuer happeneth, that they can fall vtterly from the truſt which they once conceiued of the mercies of God. <hi>Dauid</hi> was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome anguiſh and perturbation of ſpirit, when he cried, <hi>My ſoule why art thou ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed, and why art thou ſo diſquieted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me?</hi> But when he addeth by exhortation that it ſhould hope ſtill in God, he declareth
<pb facs="tcp:19226:8"/> the ſtedfaſtnes and conſtancie of his faith, wherein hee ſaith, that he was ſhut vp from the ſight of the Lorde, it ſeemed that by the great aduerſitie which hapned to him, that God had caſt him of, and quite forſaken him: yet he did not for all this leaue to call and to hope in him: ſo that in the ende he was highly exalted. And thus it happeneth oftentimes to the children of God, finding them ſelues intangled with a gulfe of euils, their hope ſeemeth to bee ſwallowed vp and drowned, although in the end it freſhly appeareth, and lifteth vp the head and comming vnto it ſelfe againe, wholy truſteth in GOD, and reſteth vnremoueable vpon his greate bountie and mercie, in which onely they glade and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themſelues, and not by any vertue or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert which is in them, aluding to that which is in the 9. Chap: of <hi>Ieremie: that he which glorieth may glorie in the Lorde,</hi> that is in his bleſſednes, and in his mercie.</p>
            <p>In this point then, conſiſteth our truſt, by the which wee muſt needes ſee what the foundation is, and how farre it reacheth, if ſo bee it bee firme and ſure, and becauſe wee ought to bee certaine and reſolued thereof, for this cauſe wee will bring foorth the holy Scripture, as wel of the Old as Newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,
<pb facs="tcp:19226:8"/> which are moſt fit and notable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the grace and mercie of God, for the forgiuenes of ſinnes, which beeing here ſet on a rowe one by another, and placed as it were on a table all in ſight, it ſhall ſerue for the inſtruction of the poore penitent ſinner, and that in this wee may keepe ſome order, we wil firſt ſhewe the teſtimonies which are apparant of the goodnes of God, which is as it were the ſureſt foundation, and the firſt cauſe of all our hope. In the ſecond place we wil adde the cauſes, which are as it were the matter and ſubſtance concerning the deſert and interceſſion of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of GOD, then the cauſes of faith and repentaunce ſhall followe, and finally that which belongeth to Inuocation and praier, theſe are the poyntes and degrees by which the faithfull ſoule ought to goe vp to the throne, and to the grace of God, for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the conſolation and Spirituall health: Firſt therefore it muſt looke vppon the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the loue and mercie of God, and the benefites of Chriſt, to haue therein a perfect knowledge, then it muſt by Faith allie, and whollie truſt vpon him, with a perfect conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of God in calling vpon him: it muſt I ſay perſwade it ſelf of the loue and mercie
<pb facs="tcp:19226:9"/> of God, and after haue full aſſurance of the merites of Chriſt, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith: it is therefore requiſite to vſe this prayer, which followeth.</p>
            <q>Of the bountie, and mercie of God. <bibl>
                  <hi>Exo. Chap. xxxiiij.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord paſſed before Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes face, hee cryed out. <hi>The Lord, the Lord ſtrong, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, and gracious, ſlowe to anger, &amp; abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; trueth, reſeruing mercie for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, forgiuing iniquitie, tranſgreſsion, and ſinne, &amp; not pardoning the wicked.</hi> As God hath created the world, mainteineth and preſerueth it, ſo doth he mainteyne, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and giues vs health and proſperitie in this life: wherein he ſhewes vnto vs his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent and eternall power, his wiſedome and wonderfull foreſight, and his great bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but in that we haue offended him by our ſinnes and iniquities, yet he receiueth vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his mercie againe, reconciling himſelf to vs, forgiuing vs our tranſgreſſions: ſo that in this hee declareth vnto vs his clemencie and infinite mercie, whereof he certifieth and
<pb facs="tcp:19226:9"/> giueth vs full aſſurance in his worde, as he doth in this place to Moſes: ſaying, that hee is not onely the eternall God almightie, but alſo mercifull and gentle: for to haue mercie and compaſſion vppon poore miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners belongeth to God: and in that he is of great patience, he ſheweth a manifeſt decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that he neuer puniſheth the wicked ſo ſoone as they offend, but a long time ſtaieth for their amendment, before he makes them feele his wrath and indignation: by which reaſon, he accompteth himſelfe to bee ſlowe to anger, and of great patience. And in the ende, that none may thinke his mercie be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhort, or ſcant, that it cannot ſuffice for diuers ſinners, he alſo addeth, that he aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in benignitie: ſhewing by the ſame, that his bountie is ſo full, that it can neuer bee emptied. He is altogether infinite, eternall, and cannot be reſtrayned, nor contayned in the heauen of heauens, nor determined in the meaſure of any time: it can neuer be ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed, being a liuely flowing ſpring, which can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be dryed vp: for moſt certaintie whereof, he maketh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of his fidelitie, repeating vp his promiſes, by which he may aſſure vs, that he will mercifull vnto vs: wherein he ſheweth himſelfe alwaies to be true, in that
<pb facs="tcp:19226:10"/> he is aboundant in benignitie, and alſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in keeping promiſe: how full of mercie he is, he declareth in that which followeth, that he is mercifull vnto thouſands: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee may learne, that he ſheweth not his mercies vnto ſome little number, or ſome particuler place, but to many hundreth and thouſands: ſhewing by this word an infinite, and the greateſt number that can be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: by which maner of ſpeech, diuerſitie of ages, and varietie of liues maye bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as it is ſayd in other places, that he is mercifull, gentle, and faithfull: in which words, he expreſſeth that he is alwaies prone and readie to forgiue our ſinnes, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our miſdeedes: wherein we ſee that the true and proper effect of God is, to haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of our ſinnes. Then to the ende, that none may think that he forgiueth ſome light offences onely, he vſeth diuers words, which comprehende all kinde of ſinnes: not only naming the ſinne whereby all offences are ſhewed, but alſo the iniquitie, which is done maliciouſly with deliberation and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led purpoſe, when iniurie or hurt is wrought againſt others. The meaning then of this worde tranſgreſſion, is a diſobedience, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious action, or intent againſt God, which
<pb facs="tcp:19226:10"/> is a greeuous and horrible ſinne: which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though of all others it be moſt deteſtable, yet God doth here promiſe to make full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and forgiuenes of ſinne. Let vs hold this then for a certaine and vnf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llible rule, that there is no forfeite ſo great, or tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſo monſterous, but it is forgiuen by the meere mercie of God. And wheras it is ſaid in the end, that he forgiueth none: it is onely ment of thoſe, which are wicked and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in their wickedneſſe, and thoſe which ſhall feele finally the ſeuere vengeaunce of God: For ſo much then as he is named gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, it is to poore and penitent ſinners, which doe repent them of their ſinnes committed: ſo is he alſo termed a iuſt Iudge, for to giue puniſhment to the hard and impenitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to the ende that none ſhould abuſe his grace and clemencie ouer much.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. Chap. 32. ver. 4.</hi>
               </bibl> Ye nations praiſe him, praiſe him his people, for he will auenge the blood of his ſeruants, and will execute vengaunce vppon his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, and will bee mercifull vnto his land, and to his people.</q>
            <p>MOſes ſpeaketh this here in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name and authoritie of GOD, as a Prophet, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:19226:11"/> the people of Iſraell, that after GOD hath viſited them with his rod, and puniſhed them with ſudden and ſtraunge calamities for their miſdeedes, he would alſo make pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of their enemies, and deliuer them from their miſeries and tribulations, being mercifull vnto the land: that is, to the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the land. The Children of Iſraell hauing purged themſelues, and made them cleane of their ſinnes by Gods mere fauour and onely mercie that he might bee alwaies fauourable towards them, and that forraine nations and ſtraunge people might praiſe the children of God, and haue them in eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and accompt them happie in hauing the fauour of ſuch a mightie God, and that thereby others ſhould haue occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce together for ſo great and bountifull benefites fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord. If then the Gentiles had receiued ſuch ioye, as to be partakers of ſo great happineſſe, we muſt needes eſteeme this promiſe to pertaine to vs alſo, and that continually, though he doth afflict vs, which is not but in good cauſe, and iuſtly for to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs for our offences. Yet he is gentle, and very ready to receiue vs into fauour of his bountifull fauour, not imputing vnto vs our iniquities, whereof wee maye haue alwaies
<pb facs="tcp:19226:11"/> cauſe to praiſe our God eternally, after that he hath drawne vs forth out of the handes of the oppreſſors and calamities of this world, and hath receiued vs into his eternall reſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 103.</hi>
               </bibl> The Lorde is full of compaſſion and mercie, ſlowe to anger, and of great kindneſſe: he will not alwaies chide, nor keepe his anger for euer. He hath not dealt with vs after our ſinnes, nor rewarded vs according to our iniquities: for as high as the heauen is aboue the earth, ſo great is his mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that feare him. As farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt: ſo farre hath he put our ſinnes from vs. As a father hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on his children: ſo hath the Lorde compaſſion on them that feare him.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He more a man is miſerable and worthy of death and damnation, the more the mercie of God ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth and ouerpaſſeth our miſerie and calamitie, which is declared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in diuers places of holy Scriptures, as it may appeare in that, which wee haue heretofore ſpoken of. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. which porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Scripture is agreable vnto this, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:19226:12"/> it containe a more ample declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (ſo great is the mercies of God) to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce and amplifie the time &amp; knowledge of him, &amp; his clemencie towards his people by the miniſtrie of his Prophetes, by whom the mercy of God is ſhewed vnto vs, either by a ſingnall promiſe by holy ſcripture, and marueilouſly amplified by compariſons, &amp; parables both fit and excellent to this ende, that we may be better perſwaded of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, and his mercie as <hi>Dauid</hi> confeſſeth, ſaying, <hi>The Lord is mercifull, gentle, ſlow to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and of great compaſsion.</hi> Theſe are the very ſelfe ſame titles which God doth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute vnto himſelfe in the place aforeſayd, wherein his nature is deſcribed vnto vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this matter concerneth our ſaluation principally, for this thing is ſhewed plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his effectes, in that he ſaith, <hi>That he is not alwaies angrie, &amp;c.</hi> for ſeeing we be diſobedient and rebellious vnto him, and do not giue him ſuch honour as wee ought, yet he pleadeth not in his wrath againſt vs, for to haue his right, and that which eſpecially doth pertaine vnto him, but that which hee doth, he doth by admonitions, reprehenſions, threatnings of his worde, corrections: that her by he may puniſh the tranſgreſſors, and
<pb facs="tcp:19226:12"/> in this maner it is ſayd, that by the ſpace of fourtie yeeres, he ſtriued in the Wildernes with a ſtubber generation, an vnthankfull people of Iſrael, as the Prophet witneſſeth in the 95. <hi>Pſal. verſ.</hi> 10. Neither leaueth he here, but doth the like with their poſteritie and ofſpring, in forbearing with their ſinnes and wickednes, as it appeareth in the firſt verſe of the 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Hoſeas,</hi> in all which places hee ſheweth himſelfe marueilous pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, when being Lord almightie, and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine iudge of all the earth, yet abaſeth him ſelfe ſo much as to contende and maintaine his right againſt ſo poore and feeble creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, whome he might haue deſtroyed and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen in a moment, if he had extended his iuſt iudgement &amp; ſeueritie againſt them, for although hee might iuſtly complaine of vs at all times, and at euery hower, becauſe of our wickedneſſe, yet hee is ſo mercifull, that he chideth vs not continually, but many times demiſſeth all complaints and ſuites, and yeeldeth vp his owne right, <hi>becauſe his mercie endureth for euer,</hi> neither doth he correct vs continually as we deſerue, neither is he angrie with vs for euer, and although he puniſh vs for our iniquities, yet not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome of men, who ſuffer them
<pb facs="tcp:19226:13"/> ſelues to bee caried away, by the rage and ſtrength of her violence and exceſſiue affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but according to the reprehenſion and feeling of thoſe, which hee ſtriketh with his rodde, and viſiteth with his Plagues, if hee ſeeme to be angrie, it is for a time, it can not continue for euer, neither laſt long. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they which be ſtriken by him, doe truely feele it, and makes their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint vnto God ſaying, why? doſt thou continue thine anger for euer? or ſhal thy wrath burne againſt the ſheepe of thy paſture? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. How long Lord ſhal thine anger continue without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. But if we conſider the greatneſſe and multitude of our ſinnes, wee ſhall finde, that the wrath of God is of ſmale continuance towards vs, ſeeing we bee not conſumed of him, we may finde him as wee imagine ſharpe, whereas on the contrary, we ſhall thinke him in his great and ineſtimable goodnes freely to forgiue vs, after ſo many ſorts and faſhions. For this cauſe it is ſaide, that his wrath continueth but a ſhort time, but in his fauour reſteth life euerlaſting: Heauines may lodge with a man one night, but ioye commeth in the morning: as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by this which followeth. The church ſpeaking vnto God, by declaring his euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb facs="tcp:19226:13"/> mercie, that although he hideth his face <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom them, and conſumeth them becauſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir ſinnes: yet in as much as they bee the worke of his owne hands, he will not ſuffer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Cittie of his Sanctuarie to lye waſte. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 54. For after that GOD had afflicted Iſrael by the <hi>Aſſerians,</hi> and troubled them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the <hi>Madianites,</hi> by the <hi>Philiſtines, Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ites,</hi> and ſuch other nations that knew not him, he ſufficiently ſheweth, that he was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie againſt his people: yet in that he raiſed vp Iudges, Heads and Captaines, by whom he deliuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the hands of their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, and gaue them quietnes and peace in the Land, wherby he cauſed them to know that his indignation was paſt, neither did it continue or laſt for euer: The captiuitie of Babilon was an euident teſtimony of the wrath of God againſt the Iewes: yet by the Commaundement and Edict of <hi>Cyrus</hi> hee brought them backe againe into their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and cauſed the people to knowe that hee had altogether ceaſed from his anger, and put away the burning of his indignation, as he ſheweth in the 85. <hi>Pſal. verſ.</hi> 4. See how he hath quieted himſelfe, and doth not hould his anger for euer. But all this which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, toucheth the faithfull onely, as for the
<pb facs="tcp:19226:14"/> vnfaithfull, which do not beleeue the wrath of God remaynes on them, as it is ſaid. <hi>Ioh. Cha.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 36. The third effect of Gods cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, &amp; the cheefeſt towards vs is, that he rewardeth vs not acccording to our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, neither correcteth vs according to our ſinnes, for the fruites and reward of ſinne is anguiſh, tribulation, damnation, and death on euery ſoule as it is written to the <hi>Rom. Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. Then if God ſhould puniſh vs, and handle vs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our deſerts, we ſhould be exceſſiuely afflicted, and continually in anguiſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende: yea, one ſhould bee alreadie ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen and deſtroyed, but in as much as he ſpareth &amp; forbeareth vs, defending vs from ſo many perrils, and deliuering vs from ſo manyfold dangers, and which is more, that he maketh vs knowe that we be his, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orneth vs with all the giftes of his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and putteth vs in hope of life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: he ſheweth manifeſtly by theſe, that he doth not reward vs according to our deſerts, neither recompence vs as we haue deſerued. By nature therefore we doe nothing but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, yet for our vnhappines hee reſtoreth goodnes againe. Wherefore it is ſayde, that there is great mercie with the Lorde, true it
<pb facs="tcp:19226:14"/> is, that ſometimes hee correcteth vs for our wickednes, but neuer chaſteneth nor puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heth vs according to our deſertes: no more then if he had not regarded them, or as they had neuer bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, ſeeing then that he remits &amp; wholy forgiues vs, by which it is ſayd, that the mercies of the Lord is ouer all his workes, and his goodnes reacheth vnto the cloudes, not that it endeth there, for it can not be contayned in the Heauen of heauens, but becauſe in this world nothing can ſeeme higher then Heauen, which is rayſed aboue the earth by an incomprehenſible diſtaunce, as it is ſaid in the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. that the goodnes of God reacheth vnto the heauens, therefore it is added afterward, that it is excellent, it is ouer our heades, it doeth ouerpaſſe our ſight, it is altogether to be marueled at, this is the height, the breadth, the deapth of the loue of Chriſt, which is ſpoken of in the 3. <hi>Chap.</hi> to the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> It is marueylous high and wonderfull to behold, it reacheth to the deepes beneath, there is nothing which the ſpirite of man can Imagine to bee greater, but onely Gods loue and bountie towardes vs, who from the higheſt Heauens, from his celeſtiall and glorious throne vouchſafeth to come to the bottomleſſe Pit of the earth, to
<pb facs="tcp:19226:15"/> drawe vs from it, and to make vs aſcende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> where hymſelfe abideth, it ſcatereth it ſelfe here and there, in length infinite, in breadth wonderfull, ſo that among ſo many regions the people may feele the vertue of it in their hearts by the holy ghoſt, and yet wee muſt knowe, that God neuer vſeth this clemencie to them which ſhewe themſelues profayned and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temners of his grace, but thoſe which doe feare him and ſheweth him honour and reuerence, therein lyeth properly the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the bountifulneſſe of the Almightie. This is againe ſhewed by a notable effect, when it is ſayde, that hee caſteth from vs our offences: as for the wicked, their malice doth not remoue, but remaynes ſtill, lying euen at the gate: as the Lord ſpeaketh of the ſinne of Cain <hi>Gen. Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. concerning the offences of the faithfull, although they be ſet before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that they doe preſent them ſelues oftentimes before the eyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule: as it happened to the Prophet, when he ſaid, that his ſinnes was continually before him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. which is nothing vnto them, but an exerciſe of true repentance, to bring them vnto humilitie, and after makes them more circumſpect: yet neuertheleſſe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Gods mercie, they be all put away:
<pb facs="tcp:19226:15"/> for he putteth them farre from him, ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them abroade, and caſteth them behinde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im, neuer to be remembred againe. Which is ſhewed by a compariſon of the diſtaunce betweene the Eaſt and the Weſt, which is the fartheſt diſtaunce that can bee imagined vnder the Sunne: euen ſo then, as the Eaſt is farre from the Weſt, and the Weſt farre from the Eaſt by a ſeparation and great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: euen ſo farre GOD doth caſt all our ſinnes away from vs: yea ſo farre, that they cannot be perceiued or no more appeare, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is carried away from one ende of the world vnto the other. And to confirme al that is ſpoken before, God is in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture compared vnto a father, which is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto his children: for as you ſee a father couer many of his ſonnes imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſeth ſuch rigour and ſeueritie towards them as he might, but ſpareth them as much as poſſiblie he can. In like maner alſo, God (who is our great and celeſtiall father) is moued with all pittie &amp; compaſſion towards vs, and readie to forgiue vs all our ſinnes: ſo that wee feare to offend him, neither doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in our iniquities.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:16"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 130.</hi>
               </bibl> If thou O Lord ſhouldſt ſtraightly marke our iniquities, O Lord who ſhould ſtand before thee: but mercie is with thee, that thou maieſt be feared. Let Iſrael waite on the Lord, for with the Lord there is mercie, and with him is great redemption, and he ſhall redeeme Jſrael from all his iniquities.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is none of vs, which are not in daunger to fall into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ruyne and deſtruction, if God ſhould looke narrowly into our ſinnes and offences, to examine them in ſeueritie, and execute a iuſt puniſhment for them: for there is no man that could ſtand before his tribunall Seate, nor bee able to iuſtifie himſelfe by his owne righteouſneſſe. Therefore Dauid in his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers and ſupplications to the Lord, deſireth him not to enter into iudgement with him, as he had deſerued. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. neither may this ſeeme ſtraunge, or ſpoken without ſpeciall purpoſe, but it is the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which the author of this Pſalm ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of here: which is done for our conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and truſt, that forgiuenes of our ſinnes only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from the Lord: neither doth he
<pb facs="tcp:19226:16"/> take any heede of them therby to condemne vs, but he ſheweth himſelfe gentle, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to vs: which made the Prophet in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion to ſay, That becauſe there is mercie with God, therefore he ſhould be feared. And that this might not be done in himſelfe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he ſtirreth vp all ſortes of men, and euery ſtate and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of nations to the due feare and true reuerence of his Maieſtie, thereby that high and lowe, rich and poore, one with an other might wholly giue themſelues to ſerue him in thankfulneſſe and heauenly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodie: for the more he powreth on vs his bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and mercifull liberalitie, the more we are bound to him, and ought to be much more deſirous to ſerue him in holineſſe and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe all the daies of our life. So that the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes is ioyned with the honor and glorie of GOD, and our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which ought to followe his grace, not onely particulerly, but alſo generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all true Chriſtians. For, for this cauſe Dauid doth giue certaine aſſuraunce vnto the Catholicke Church of GOD, vnder the name of Iſrael: ſaying, that the Lord would deliuer Iſrael from all his iniquities, and purge them from all their ſinnes: &amp; although the Church be not without ſinne during the
<pb facs="tcp:19226:17"/> time that it is in this earthly perigrination, but hath wrinckles and ſpots ſubiect to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny infirmities and tranſgreſſions, by whom it is as it were made captiue and brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bondage: yet God will deliuer it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally out of ſuch miſerie, and by his infinite mercie forgiue it not ſome faults onely, but all her iniquities how great ſoeuer they bee, and of what number ſoeuer. Vpon this hope then, the Prophet exhorteth the Church to truſt in the Lorde, hoping in him in time of oppreſſion, when wee are in diſtreſſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame affliction. In as much as there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of mercie with him, he wanteth no meanes to redeeme and drawe his out of anguiſh and tribulation: his waies are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, he needeth no good affection, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined and giuen by his owne nature to cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie and mercie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſay Chap. 1. ver. 18.</hi>
               </bibl> Though your ſinnes were as Crimſin, they ſhal be made white as Snowe: though they were made red like Skarlet, they ſhalbe as wooll.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is an excellent and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble promiſe, which God hath made to his auncient people, that of his
<pb facs="tcp:19226:17"/> mercie he hath put all their ſinnes out of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, euen as though they had neuer bene committed: were they neuer ſo great and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, yet Gods mercie is greater: &amp; therfore they ought not to diſpayre. The Prophet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth the ſmall honor they ſhewed to God, and their wonderfull imperfections, when he giueth vnto them ſuch opprobrius titles, calling them rebellious Children, a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Vipers, a people altogether giuen to iniquitie, a wicked ſeede, baſe borne, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt children, yea, ſparing none, no not one: he ſayth that they are all naught, from the greateſt to the loweſt, from the head to the foote, both Prieſt and people, Mageſtrate and ſubiect are like to them of Zodome, and as the inhabitaunce of Gomorra, all defiled with murther, &amp; ſhedding of innocent blood: yet GOD doth promiſe that he will neuer bring their ſinnes to accompt, bee their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities neuer ſo greeuous and monſtrous, as the compariſon of colours, euen of the red and bloudy colour, of the Skarlet and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple dye ſheweth: yet the Lord will make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as wooll, yea, as white as the driuen ſnowe, then the which, what can be whiter? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord ſetteth downe theſe wordes, to aſſure vs, by fit and probable ſimilitudes, that
<pb facs="tcp:19226:18"/> although their ſinnes were ripe, and as it were dyed in graine, which will not eaſily alter or chaunge the colour: yet they ſhall be no more remembred, nor once appeare again before him, no more then the olde colour is knowne which hath taken on it a newe dye: So all the filthineſſe and infamie that was found in them ſhall bee made very pure, and very cleane. And after this ſort doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet pray, that if God would waſh, purifie, and make him cleane againe from his ſinne, then he ſhould bee whiter then Snowe, and clearer, yea farre clearer then the Chriſtall glaſſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. And although it may ſeeme, that this promiſe was made particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary to the Iewes: yet notwithſtanding it doth appertaine to vs alſo, that hereby wee might knowe, that the mercie of God is no leſſe towardes vs, nor his arme ſhortned in our daies: but rather more amply declared, and ſhewed by the comming of his Sonne, and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:18"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſay Chap. 43. ver. 25.</hi>
               </bibl> I, euen I am he that putteth away thyne ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities for myne owne ſake, and will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy ſinnes.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough our ſinnes be as thei were written with a pen of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, &amp; with a diamond poynt, and profoundly engrauen in the tables of our harts, and in our ſoules, &amp; noted by too much apparance: neuertheleſſe the Lord our God doth certifie vs here, of the forgiueneſſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is himſelfe, which doth blot, put out, &amp; rayſe them in ſuch ſort, that they are not to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued any more, neither doe they appeare at any time before his face, no otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if they had neuer bene committed, hee I ſay blotteth them out, not for one day, nor for certaine monethes or yeres, or for ſome ſpace of time preſcribed or limited, but continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and to the laſt gaſpe, which is ſhewed by this phraſe of ſpeaking, for this word to blot out, is a perpetuall extinguiſhing of that, which hath bin manifeſted neuer to be in the like ſtate againe, whereby we may learne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue al neede of his great grace, not for a time, but vnto the end of our life, yea ſo long
<pb facs="tcp:19226:19"/> as ſinne ſhal remaine in vs, for wee are euer moleſted and greeued, and therforefore haue neede of mercie, as it is declared in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 23.24. and in that hee ſaith, that it is he himſelfe, which blotteth out our iniquities, he ſheweth none other can do it but he, neither is there any creature either in heauen or in earth, that hath ſuch power either in themſelues, or from themſelues. Now then we muſt learne, how this can be true, ſeeing it is ſayd, that the Apoſtles and Shepherds of the Church of God haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſuch authoritie to forgiue ſinnes, as in <hi>S. Math. Chap.</hi> 18. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. and <hi>S. Iohn. Chap.</hi> 20. <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. but this is by reaſon of their charge and miniſtry, and not that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to them ſelues properly, they may in deede remit the offences committed, but by and in the name of the Lorde, to whome they be Herraltes and Ambaſſadours, it then belongeth vnto God onely to remit ſinnes, for the which he will haue vs to be fully aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in conſidering that it is himſelfe which doth ſpeake it, and which maketh this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, euen he, which is eternall and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: euen he, which is good and full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: this repetition and maner of ſpeaking belongeth to him, in that it is ſayde: I my
<pb facs="tcp:19226:19"/> ſelfe forgiue ſinnes to this end, that we may not in any wiſe doubt, but therein wholy be perſwaded by what meanes he is moued and ſtirred vp, for in blotting out our ſinnes, hee declareth that it is for his name ſake, it is not then for any worthineſſe in vs, nor in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of any deſerts of ours: Neither ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by any Saints or indulgences found out by mans imagination, but by his free bountie, according to that which Dauid doth deſire of the Lord, that according to his great compaſſion, hee would blot out our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 51. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. He addeth alſo for the confirmation of this, that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before, that he will not bring our ſinnes to account, not that he is forgetfull, for wee muſt knowe, that all things be preſent vnto him, and before his eyes: but this is to ſhew, that he will not bring them to account, for to make puniſhment of them againe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſay. Chap. 44. verſ. 22.</hi>
               </bibl> I haue put away thy tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſions like a cloude, and thy ſinnes like a Miſt, turne vnto mee for I haue redeemed thee.</q>
            <p>FOraſmuch as ſinne is nothing but filth and durt, wherewith we be all infected and abhominably polluted, behold God
<pb facs="tcp:19226:20"/> which ſaith that hee himſelfe blotteth them out, not in halfe, nor in ſome part, but wholy, and altogether: neither more, nor leſſe, but as a very thicke and darke cloude, which by the abundance and force of raine, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing waters doe take and carry away with them ſelues the filthines of the earth: ſo we when we be waſhed, and purified from ſuch filthines, and faultes, hee will not haue vs returne backe againe vnto the mud, there to defile our ſelues, but willeth vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue with him, ſetting vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faire way and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which doth appertaine vnto him, not onely by nature &amp; creation, but alſo by right of redemption, for he is our redeemer, and our pledge, which hath redemed vs, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs againſt all enimies.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mich. Chap. 7. verſ. 18.</hi>
               </bibl> Who is a God like vnto the Lord, that taketh away iniquitie, &amp; paſſeth by the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the remnant of his heritage, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth not his wrath for euer, becauſe mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy pleaſeth him, hee will turne againe and haue compaſſion, he will ſubdue our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and caſt all our ſinnes into the bottom of the ſea, thou wilt performe thy trueth to
<pb facs="tcp:19226:20"/> Iacob, and mercie to Abraham, as thou haſt ſworne to our fathers in old time.</q>
            <p>TRuely there is none that may bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto God, either in gentlenes, or in power: for he and none other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth ſinne, and although he met a ſinner in the way, (becauſe all thinges bee preſent vnto him) yet he will not ſtay himſelfe to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, but depart farther of, as though he took no heede what is done, and leaue behind him the offence committed. By this maner of ſpeech it is ſayd, that God caſteth our ſinnes backe from him. <hi>Eſay Chap.</hi> 38. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. yet onely to thoſe which do properly appertaine vnto him, whom he doth auouch &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for his inheritance, and peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who are of that Church, to whome hee graunteth grace, from which all others bee ſequeſtred. And be it, that ſometymes he doth anger himſelfe, and his wrath be mooued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne iuſtly: yet it is not of long continuaunce, in ſo much that hee is rather prone to mercie and clemencie, then to ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and rigor. And although he ſeeme by our offences and vices to turne himſelf back from vs, and to afflict vs, as we deſerue: yet he will returne againe, and wil ſhewe vs the
<pb facs="tcp:19226:21"/> cherefull and comfortable light of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, in ſhewing compaſſion on vs, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueth all our ſinnes, by putting downe and deſtroying all the viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and force of death: ſo that we are no more houlden in captiuitie and bondage, but made free, and ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by him, not by caſting them on the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d onely, but by deſtroying, and deliuering vs from them, by throwing them into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Sea, that they may appeare no more, but the memorie of them paſſe away, as a thing which is bound vp and caſt into the deepeſt Sea. And in this we ſee, that he is not mooued for any worthineſſe that is in vs, but of his onely bountie and clemencie, being gentle and full of mercie, ſlowe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and of great goodneſſe by nature, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in his promiſes which he made vnto the fathers, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by his oth, and in theſe latter tymes fulfilled the bountifulneſſe of his mercie in his onely Sonne: who is the onely pledge to aſſure vs of the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes. And wheras the Prophet ſaith that God doth not onely forgiue our ſinnes, but paſſeth them ouer, not by putting them downe onely, but caſting them into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Sea, for to aboliſh them wholly: it cannot be more plainly expreſſed or decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:19226:21"/> how God forgiueth vs. Then, if in the tyme of the lawe and ſhadowes, his promiſe was not in vaine: how much ought we now to be more certaine of it vnder the kingdome of Chriſt, by whome wee obtaine trueth and grace?</p>
            <p>The grace of GOD towardes vs, by meanes of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ieremy Chap. 31. ver. 31.</hi>
               </bibl> Beholde the day is come, ſayth the Lord, that I will make a new couenant with the houſe of Jſrael, and with the houſe of Iuda. J will put my law in their inward parts, &amp; write it in their hearts, and wilbe their God, and they ſhall be my people: I will pardon their iniquities, and will remember their ſinnes no more.</q>
            <p>THis is the holy and happie alliaunce, that wee obtaine with God by Ieſus Chriſt his Sonne, by whome, albeit we bee ſufficiently taught, and inſtructed in the knowledge of his trueth, both in wil and affection to obey him, according to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, yet we goe oftentimes aſtray, and doe againſt his deuine precepts, by the wickedneſſe and imperfections which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes
<pb facs="tcp:19226:22"/> in vs: wherefore we haue alwayes neede of his grace, for the remiſſion of our ſinnes, in the promiſe which hee hath made vnto vs, as wee are taught in this place of Scripture: which although it was made in the auncient couenant of the lawe wherein al things alſo are included, yet it partaineth properly vnto the newe promiſe, obtained by Ieſus Chriſt the very Sonne of GOD, the ſure foundation and perfect ſubſtance of our ſaluation: for he is the mediator of the newe Teſtament, as it is ſayd in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Heb. Chap.</hi> 9. It is he by whoſe deſert all our ſinnes are forgiuen, which could not bee remitted by the outward figures, and vaine ſhadowes of the lawe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſay Chap. 53. ver. 4.</hi>
               </bibl> Surely he hath borne our infirmities, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried our ſorrowes: he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, &amp; broken for our iniquities: the chaſtiſment of our peace was vpon him, and with his ſtripes wee are healed. The Lord hath layd vpon him the iniquities of vs all, by his knowledge ſhall my iuſt ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t iustifie many, for he ſhall beare their ſinnes.</q>
            <p>AS God is by nature gentle and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo is he a ſeuere and iuſt Iudge: for
<pb facs="tcp:19226:22"/> he leaueth not ſinne vnpuniſhed, but layeth the puniſhment of it vpon his onely Sonne, who in the fulneſſe of time deliuered him for vs vnto the ſhamefull and accurſed death of the Croſſe, wherein his iuſtice and mercie is founde by ioyning both together in an inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable bond of vnitie. And firſt in that, that Ieſus Chriſt ſuffered for our iniquities: the other in that, that he was well pleaſed to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his Sonne to be a pledge, and an attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for vs. This then the Prophet teacheth in this place, that Chriſt hath ſuffered for vs an infinite number of greefes, torments, and puniſhments, as touching his ſoule: he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a death full of ſhame and reproch in the worlde, to iuſtifie and deliuer vs from dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and eternal death, acquiting vs from the wrath of God. Seeing then, that in hart and affection wee acknowledge him for our tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sauiour and Redeemer, we neede not to feare, although we ſhall perceiue, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſelues to be guiltie: yet wee may bee aſſured, that wee are in peace with God, becauſe Ieſus Chriſt our Redeemer hath borne the paines due for our iniquities. If Sathan then doe aſſaile vs by terrible i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations of the paines and torments, which we haue iuſtly deſerued in reſpect of
<pb facs="tcp:19226:23"/> our iniquities, let vs preſent our ſelues in the rightuouſneſſe and holineſſe of Ieſus Chriſt: for he hath borne our greefes, &amp; layde our ſorowes on him: he hath bene wounded, hurt, and murthered: he died for vs which are vniuſt, and roſe againe for our ſanctification, to the end he might iuſtifie and abſolue vs.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zach. Chap. 12. ver. 1.</hi>
               </bibl> In that day there ſhalbe a fountaine opened to the houſe of Dauid, and to the inhabitants of Ieruſalem for ſinne, and for vncleannes.</q>
            <p>THis is the fayre and cleare fountaine of grace, the liuely water that floweth to vs by Ieſus Chriſt, by the ſhedding of his precious blood, which is opened to all thoſe which are of the houſhold of God, and made Citizens of the heauenly and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Ieruſalem, which is the true Church wherein they waſh and purge their ſinnes. Let vs therefore goe vnto this liuely water, and into this life euerlaſting, where the one neuer ſtayeth running, and cannot be dryed vp, nor the poſſeſſors of the other ſhall euer taſte of the ſecond death: for this ſpring flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in great aboundance, ſo that we ſhalbe waſhed faire and cleane, bee our iniquities neuer ſo foule and polluted.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:23"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math. Chap. 11. ver. 18.</hi>
               </bibl> Come vnto me all ye that are wearie and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie laden, and J will refreſh you.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He admirable and bountifull loue of the Lorde Ieſus is in this place ſhewed, in that he vouchſafeth to helpe and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour thoſe, which be poore and in miſerie, he will not caſt them away, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſend them to others to make their mone and complaints: but he calleth them himſelf vnto him, I ſay he, which is the very Sonne of God, the Lord of glory, calleth thoſe vnto him which are oppreſſed, &amp; troubled in their conſciences by the feeling of their ſinnes, and therefore promiſeth to ayde them, and giue them reſt, the true tranquilitie and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie quietneſſe of the ſoule: Let vs goe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to Ieſus Chriſt our onely Sauiour and redeemer: let vs goe in a true faith, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſeeing he ſtretcheth forth his armes to receiue vs: ſeing he is ſweet, ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle, mercifull, of great goodneſſe. Are we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heauy loden with the burthen of our ſinnes? he will deliuer vs from the yoke and ſeruitude of the houſe of bondage. Are we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hayled, and tyed by the tyrannie of ſinne
<pb facs="tcp:19226:24"/> and death? he will preſerue vs from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude of the one, and from the deadly ſting of the other.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn Chap. 1. ver. 29.</hi>
               </bibl> Behold the Lambe of God, which taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſinnes of the world.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is the teſtimonie that Iohn the Baptiſt witneſſeth openly of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who was orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſent of God to be the Lambe (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fault, without ſpotte) which in former times was figured in ſundry Sacrifices of the law, yet more eſpecially in the Paſſouer or Lambe, which was offred euery day, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and euening for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes of the Prieſt, and people: but this Lambe, when none was worthy to offer him vp to his father, hath wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly offered himſelfe, that by dying once for al, he might obtaine forgiuenes of ſinnes for all: and by this meanes he hath brought vs vnto God the father, that he might conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, not for once acquite, and deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſinnes, which is ſhewed more forcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if wee marke the worde which he vſeth <hi>(he doth take away)</hi> which is declared in the tyme preſent, and that by the merite of his death, which is alwaies of one and the
<pb facs="tcp:19226:24"/> ſame vertue, and perpetual efficacie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we obtaine our eternall redemption: as it is ſayd by the author to the <hi>Heb. Chap.</hi> 9. And this benefite being ſo precious &amp; great, ſerueth not for one, or two onely, neither for one onely Nation, but reacheth ouer al peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and euery Nation of the earth, as this word <hi>(world)</hi> proueth. Let vs not then doubt that our ſinnes are remitted by the death of Chriſt, whoſe death ſhould nothing auayle vs, if we ſhould not receiue the fruite of it by faith in his promiſes, ſeeing that ſinne dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in vs continually, as it is prooued in the 7. Chapter to the <hi>Romaines.</hi> Therefore we receiue pardon for them continually by him, who hath brought vs to the throne of grace, where with boldneſſe we may call his father abba our father.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts Chap. 5. ver. 31.</hi>
               </bibl> This is that Jeſus, which God hath lifted vp with his right hand, to bee a Prince and a Sauiour, to giue repentaunce to Iſrael, and forgiuenes of ſinnes.</q>
            <p>THe Empyre and ſoueraigne dominion of Chriſt is here ſhewed vnto vs by <hi>S. Peter,</hi> to the ende, he might declare vnto vs the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb facs="tcp:19226:25"/> &amp; ſpirituall libertie, which he beſtoweth on his Church, meaning his people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: that is to ſay, that by him our ſinnes are remitted, with chaunge of newneſſe of life, promiſed to our eternall ſaluation. Theſe two graces then being ioyned together, can neuer bee ſeperated, that thereby none may doubt of the obtayning of this excellent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite purchaſed by the Lord Ieſus: which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would pull back from his highnes, and debate his power, who will for theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites be honoured in word, and glorified in deede.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts Chap. 13. ver. 38.</hi>
               </bibl> Be it knowne vnto you, that through this man (our Sauiour Chriſt) is preached vnto you forgiuenes of ſinnes.</q>
            <p>THis place is like vnto the former, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the benefite purchaſed by Chriſt, by whom we obtayne forgiuenes of our ſinnes: a thing worthy of all men to bee had in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, of the which euery man ought to bee certaine, and reſolued in the aſſurance of his ſaluation.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:25"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. Chap. 5. ver. 8.</hi>
               </bibl> God ſheweth his loue towards vs, ſeeing that while wee were yet ſinners Chriſt dyed for vs, much more now being iustified by his blood: we ſhalbe ſaued from wrath through him, for if when we were enemies we were reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled to God by the death of his ſonne, much more being reconciled, ſhalbe ſaued by his life, and not onely ſo, but alſo reioyce in God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, by whom we haue obtayned reconciliation.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is to aſſure vs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue and mercie of God towardes vs, and of our ſaluation, when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what Chriſt Ieſus hath done for vs, who beeing the Sonne of God, iuſt, and innocent, ſuffered ſo many torments for vs vniuſt, and guiltie, ſo that now wee are purged, and made cleare of al our faults and iniquities: yea, we are acquited and abſolued from the wrath and anger of GOD: who is wholly quieted, peace being made betweene him and vs by the reconciliation of the Lord Ieſus, who is the meanes, by the vertue of his death, and preſeruer of our life by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power of his dietie: for our life is hid in him, &amp; our death is buried in him: in him
<pb facs="tcp:19226:26"/> therefore all our glory conſiſteth, for there is nothing wherein wee may glory our ſelues, nor our works, but onely in the great fauour and mercie of our God, and in the grace and mercie of our Lorde and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn 1. Epiſt. 1. Chap. ver. 7.</hi>
               </bibl> The blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all our ſinnes.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough we bee guiltie, and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with many ſinnes, which are in the eyes of the Lorde ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and filthie: yet the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth aſſure vs, that wee are waſhed and purified from them, not by any counterfeite water of mans fancie, nor by a fayned ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of fire in Purgatorie, in any other worlde, neither by the blood of Martyrs, as ſome haue falſly taught, but only by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood of the Sonne of God: which is of ſuch efficacie, and continuall vertue, that he can blot out our ſinnes perticularly how many ſoeuer they be.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:26"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn 1. Epiſt. Chap. 2. ver. 1.</hi>
               </bibl> If any man ſinne, wee haue an aduocate with the father Ieſus Chriſt the rightuous, and he is the reconciliation for our ſinnes, and not for ours onely, but alſo the ſinnes of the whole world.</q>
            <p>THere is none without ſinne, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently al are guiltie before GOD: yet behold the Apoſtle witneſſeth, that the Lord Ieſus Chriſt doth pray, and make requeſt for vs: as it is ſayd in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines Chap.</hi> 8. and to the <hi>Heb. Chap.</hi> 7. which interceſſion betweene God and man was of ſuch force and vertue, that no others but he was found worthie and able to make vs vnderſtande the gentle and fauourable goodwill of God the father: for he dyed for our ſinnes, &amp; vndertooke to make an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reconciliation for our miſdeedes to God: which excellent and worthy deſert is not onely reſtrayned to ſome particuler perſon, but reacheth to all generally, that all might perceiue the loue of their Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:27"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn 1. Epiſt. Chap. 3. ver. 10.</hi>
               </bibl> In this are the children of God knowne, and the children of the deuill: whoſoeuer doth not rightly is not of God, neither he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not his brother: and this is appoynted a reward for ſinnes.</q>
            <p>THis place is like vnto the place afore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, contayning more fully the loue, and mercifulneſſe of GOD towards vs, in that he hath brought vs againe vnto him by his welbeloued Sonne, who gaue himſelfe for vs.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Of faith in Chriſt, Ioh. Cap. 3. ver. 16.</hi>
               </bibl> God ſo loued the world, that he hath giuen his onely begotten ſonne, that whoſoeuer belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlasting.</q>
            <p>THe beginning and firſt cauſe of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is in GOD, who in his mercie and fatherly loue ſaued vs. The ſecond is in Chriſt, who by the merite of his death &amp; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion redeemed vs: the onely inſtrument and meanes to obtain ſuch great good is by faith in Ieſus Chriſt, which is of ſuch vertue and efficacie, that by it man is reconciled vnto
<pb facs="tcp:19226:27"/> God by the free remiſſion of ſinne: wherfore he cannot fall vtterly in as much as he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from eternall death, and made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of an happie life.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn. Chap. 5. verſ. 24.</hi>
               </bibl> Verely, verely I ſay vnto you, he that heareth my words and beleeueth in him that ſent me, hath euerlaſting life: and ſhal not come into condemnation, but paſſeth from death to life.</q>
            <p>THis is to confirme our ſelues in the aſſurance wee haue in Chriſt, and in the certaine perſwaſion of his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, when as wee doe vnderſtand that our faith reſting in him, is not founded vppon a mortall man, but on the very and true ſonne of God, wherefore it is ſayde that we are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified: that wee are ſanctified in and by the bloud of Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Rom. Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. we be abſolued from our ſinnes, neither can bee condemned any wiſe, beeing ſo war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by him, which is eternall, by whome we obtaine life and felicitie, which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for euer.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:28"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. Chap. 10. verſ. 9.</hi>
               </bibl> If thou ſhalt confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Ieſus, and ſhalt beleeue in thy heart that God rayſed him vp from death, thou ſhalt be ſaued.</q>
            <p>HOw eaſie the way of ſaluation is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſheweth in this place, not vſing many words, neither ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs backe to the profound and deepe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of almightie God, but giueth vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that by the grace of God which is in vs, we are ſaued if ſo be we hould faſt the faith, not lightly in the Braine, but rooted profoundly in the heart, apprehending per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Ieſus Chriſt: which once died for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iuſtification, as it is in the 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> of this Epiſtle. And although the confeſſion of the mouth bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: which principally ſerueth for an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teſtimony, and a manifeſt declaration of the hope which is in vs, yet eſpecially wee muſt haue the heart lyne lye touched with a ſure perſwaſion of faith, whoſe mouth will not bee ſtopped. Seeing that with the heart we beleeue: and with the mouth declare our iuſtification, &amp; as the Prophet ſaith in 116. <hi>Pſalme. verſ.</hi> 10. I haue beleeued, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue ſpoken.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:28"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts Chap. 10. ver. 43.</hi>
               </bibl> To him do all the Prophets giue witneſſe, that through his name all that beleeue in him might receiue remiſſion of ſinne.</q>
            <p>IT is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the meanes of faith in Chriſt, that we doe obtaine forgiueneſſe of ſinne if ſo be we aſſure and reſt our ſelues who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vppon the merrit and interceſſion of him, following the predictions and writings not only of the Prophets, but of thoſe alſo which haue Propheſied in the vnitie of the ſame ſpirite, whereby we attaine fully all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of eternall life, by and through the meanes of Chriſt Ieſus, and let this be for a full confirmation of this Article.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Repentance.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſo much as the grace of God and ſaluation hath appeared to al men, to the end we might giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer al vnfaithfulneſſe and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires, and that we ſhould liue iuſtly in all chriſtianitie, ſeeing we be bought by the bloud of the immaculate La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be Ieſus Chriſt, and therefore ought to bee vnto him a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar people, giuen vnto all good workes, for
<pb facs="tcp:19226:29"/> this cauſe we muſt take great heede, that we abuſe not the great benignitie and long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance of God, by continuing in ſinne and iniquitie, which is the only meanes to heape vppon vs his wrath and vengeaunce to our condemnation. For whenſoeuer we erre or fall into ſinne, whether it be by the imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our nature, or frailtie of our fleſh (ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient meanes to heape the burning coles of Gods ſeueritie vpon vs, if in iudgement hee ſhould ſtand againſt vs) yet we muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre from day to day: but rent our heartes not our garments, and in earneſt contrition of our ſoules, and ſincere repenting by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing our miſerable eſtate, and deſirous to bee looſed from the heauie burden of our ſinnes, ſhewe all duetie and amendement of life. For as ſaint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, that the firſt degree of our felicitie, is to commit no ſinne: ſo the ſecond is to acknowledge our ſinne committed. Therefore whenſoeuer we fall (as who is not vncleane in the eyes of his Creator: And the righteous man ſinneth ſeauen times aday) yet we muſt not lye gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueling on the ground, but rayſe vp our ſelues by faith in the promiſes of God, &amp; in the hope of eternall life, aſſuring our ſelues, that he will receiue vs to mercie, and ſpred
<pb facs="tcp:19226:29"/> vpon vs his grace: for he is our Shepheard, and wee ſhall not want: he hath placed vs as a ſignet on his finger, and printed vs in the palme of his right hand, ſo that none ſhall be able to plucke vs of, or blot vs out of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, but of his mercie he hath rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated vs, and made vs partakers of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward waſhing ſealed into vs in the outward Baptiſme, and grafting vs into the bodie of Chriſt by receiuing vs into his Church, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be hereafter excluded from his grace, and forgiueneſſe of ſinne, though wee fall by infirmitie into the ſame ſinne againe: which may bee a confutation of the irronious and deteſtable opinion of the <hi>Nouations,</hi> rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed by certaine Heritickes in our time, but ſufficiently reproued and condemned by the fathers out of the word of God: For ſeeing the promiſes of God bee made onely for his people and his Church, through grace and mercie vnto them, which may appeare in the effects of the ſame, by notable example of worthy memorie hereafter declared, that if in the tyme of the Law and old Teſtament, GOD hath ſhewed himſelfe fauourable to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe, which of good wil haue drawne themſelues towardes him: how much more will hee ſpred abroade the bright beames of
<pb facs="tcp:19226:30"/> his mercie to vs, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raigne of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, by whom and through whom he maketh vs free inheritours of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of his grace. Let vs ſee now what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration wee haue of theſe thinges in holy Scripture.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Deut. Chap. 4. ver. 30.</hi>
                  </bibl> When thou art in tribulation, and all theſe things are come vpon thee, if thou returne to the Lord thy God, and be obedient to his voyce, for the Lord thy God is a mercifull God, he will not forſake thee, neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, nor forget he ſware to thy fathers to performe it.</q>
               <p>MOſes ſpeaketh in this place vnto vs vnder the perſon of the people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, that thereby wee might make our ſelues ſure, that if by the vanities of our mynde wee commit Idolatrie, and worſhip ſtrange Gods, therby corrupting our ſelues, and deſeruing the wrath of our God vpon vs, by falling into diuers euilles and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: yet if wee repent, and bee diſpleaſed with our ſelues in hauing offended ſuch a mercifull GOD, and deſiring to ſerue him hereafter in holineſſe and rightuouſneſſe all
<pb facs="tcp:19226:30"/> the daies of our life, he will ceaſe from puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and performe his promiſes made in and by the meditation of his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm. 51. ver. 19.</hi>
                  </bibl> The ſacrifice of God is a holy ſpirite, a contrite and broken heart, O Lorde thou wilt not deſpiſe.</q>
               <p>THeſe are the wordes of Dauid, which he ſetteth downe as a patterne and example of a true penitent man, ſtrucken by the ſpirit of God, who declareth vnto vs, that in the feeling of his weakenes and vnworthines, he is ouercome, he is afflicted in his ſoule, and ſorowfull in his heart, complayning for his ſinnes, watering his couch with his tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, greeuouſly pained lyeth groning all the day long, he repenteth that he hath done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, he humbleth himſelfe before his God in Sackcloth and Aſhes: This is the man whoſe Sacrifice the Lorde receiueth, whoſe broken and contrite hart he neuer deſpiſeth: who pleaſeth him more then all the Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Beaſts y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue hornes and houfes, then the offrings of their newe Monies, and the giftes of high and proude hippocrites,
<pb facs="tcp:19226:31"/> then all the vanities of the ſuperſticious I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatours, which thinke to honour and ſerue him with any faith and repentance.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prouer. Chap. 28. ver. 13.</hi>
                  </bibl> He that hideth his ſinnes ſhall not proſper, but he that confeſſeth and forſaketh them, ſhall haue mercie.</q>
               <p>THe holy Ghoſt doth certifie vs here, that although there can no euill happen vnto him, which humbleth himſelf before God by acknowledging his ſinne, and that there is grace, forgiueneſſe &amp; mercie offered to thoſe which feele themſelues guilty, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their tranſgreſſions, aſking abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and deliuerance by a true ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dment of life. I doe thinke this place of Scripture prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to be touched among the reſt, becauſe the holy Ghoſt of purpoſe ſetteth it downe to comfort the penitent Sinner, which are very ſorie that they haue offended ſo heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a father, who is of long ſuffring and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who is in Scripture named the God of all comfort and conſolation: and therefore they will not hide their ſinne, but confeſſe it vnto the Lord, who will heale all their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and cleanſe them from their ſinnes:
<pb facs="tcp:19226:31"/> for the Lord is mercifull vnto al ſuch as call vpon him, yea, al ſuch as call vpon him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. Haſt thou then bene a blaſphemer, a robber, a lyer? Haſt thou giuen thy ſelfe to Vſurie? Art thou couetous? Haſt thou bene a Fornicator? an Adulterer? If thou leaue thy blaſphemie, forſake thy euill doing, ſhun couetouſnes as a Serpent: if thou flye from the paths of the ſtrange woman, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious pampering of the belly: if thou flyeſt from euill, and doeſt the thing that is good: if thou abhorreſt the boſome of the light wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp; the alluring bed of the Harlot: doubt not, but thy ſinnes be forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the debt payd, the wrath of God againſt thee is pacified by the ſight of the Lambe which ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth on the Mount. Heare the wiſedome of God, which ſayth, he that leaueth his ſinne ſhall obtaine mercie: Haſt thou then left thy wickedneſſe? Art thou become a newe man? Haſt thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended thy euill life? God will ſhewe thee mercie and compaſſion: we neede not to goe farre to ſeeke proofes and teſtimonies of the grace of God towards vs, the very amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our life is an euident demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtration of the ſame, which the Prophet Dauid felt in the 32. Pſal: when he ſayth, then I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged my ſinne vnto thée, neither did I hide
<pb facs="tcp:19226:32"/> myne iniquitie: for I thought, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe againſt my ſelfe my wickedneſſe vnto the Lord, and thou forgaueſt the puniſhment of my fault. Therefore ſhall euery one that is godly make his praier vnto thee in a time when thou maiſt be found: ſurely the flood of great water ſhall not come nere him. Thou art my ſecret place, thou preſerueſt me from my trouble, and compaſſes me about with ioyfull deliuerance.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eſay Chap. 55. ver. 7.</hi>
                  </bibl> Seeke ye the Lord while he may be found, call vpon him while he is neere. Let the wicked forſake his owne waies, and the vnrightuous his owne imaginations, and returne vnto the Lord, &amp; he will haue mercie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, for he is ready to forgiue. For my thoughtes are not as your thoughtes, neither are your waies as my waies ſaith the Lorde. For as the heauens are higher then the earth: ſo are my waies higher then your waies, and my thoughts aboue your thoughts.</q>
               <p>ALthough by our offences we eſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and withdrawe our ſelues greatly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, he is neuertheleſſe nere at hand if we draw our ſelues from our euill and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:19226:32"/> life: if we be touched with a true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: if wee commit our ſelues vnto him: if we call vpon him with all our hearts, &amp; with all our ſoules, we may be ſure he wilbe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto vs, as the Prophet ſayth. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our ſinnes abound, yet his mercie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth much more: though our iniquities (as we thinke) are infinite, and without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, not eſteeming the goodnes and clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, according to his greatneſſe and infinite mercies, but according to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and frailtie of our vnderſtanding: yet wee ſee that the Lorde ſheweth by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that his thoughtes and his workes doe ſurpaſſe all that is in vs, or can come from vs. For although our ſinnes were in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as the ſande of the Sea, or as the ſtarres of Heauen: yet we know that he holdeth the Sea in his hand, and calleth the Starres by their names: for as the Heauen is in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the Earth, ſo are his mercies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all that call vpon him. Why ſhould any then miſtruſt the benignitie of GOD, ſeeing he is ſo carefull to aſſure vs of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of our ſinnes, whenſoeuer we doe call vpon him.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19226:33"/>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Exech. Chap. 18. ver. 21.</hi>
                  </bibl> If the wicked will turne from his ſinnes, that he hath committed, and keepe all my ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and doe all that is lawfull and right, he ſhal ſurely liue, and not dye: al his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions which he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ſhall not be mentioned vnto him. Haue J any deſire that the wicked ſhould dye, ſaith the Lord, or ſhall hee not liue if he retourne from his waies? Therfore returne and repent you for your tranſgreſſions, ſo iniquitie ſhall not bee your destruction. Caſt away from you all your tranſgreſſions, wherby you haue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and make you a newe heart, and a newe ſpirite: for why will you dye O houſe of Iſrael.</q>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord in this place ſpeaketh not directly vnto the ſinner, which fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth by frailtie and weakeneſſe of fleſh, but to the wicked, which of mallice and crueltie hath robbed and ſhed innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t blood, who hath oppreſſed the needie, and ſolde the poore for olde ſhooes, who hath whined after his neighbours wife, &amp; hath bene partakers with the Adulterers: which haue runned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bethel to Dan, and from Dan to Bethel to ſerue ſtraunge Gods: which haue ſacrificed
<pb facs="tcp:19226:33"/> of their owne fleſh to Molocke, and haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the offringes of the dead: to theſe which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nke ſinne as water, and drawe iniquitie with cords: to theſe I ſay ſpeaketh the Lord, and telleth them, that if they doe truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent them of all their miſdeedes which they haue committed, they ſhal neuer be imputed to them againe, they ſhall be deliuered from them, and made partakers of eternall life, if his repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be true, not fained, but yeelds himſelf wholly to ſerue his God, though his obedience be imperfect, and there bee ſome want in him: yet hee ſhall bee waſhed in the blood of the Lambe, by his woundes he ſhall be healed, and in his weakeneſſe he ſhall bee made ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: he ſhalbe holy, becauſe he which hath called him is holy. And in this reſpect are Chriſtians called oftentymes iuſt in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, though there bee ſome imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in them daylie to bee ſeene, yet this is ſhewed to declare the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful and great bountie and clemencie of God towards vs, that hauing offended him in breaking his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces, and ſo made guiltie of eternall death: yet that he vouchſafeth to call vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto him, and to ſtretch forth his arme all the day long to take vs vp when we were fallen, and exhorteth vs to repentaunce, and
<pb facs="tcp:19226:34"/> to newneſſe of life, which is the token and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident teſtimonie of a true conuerſion and newe regeneration by the holy Ghoſt. And whereas he commaundeth vs to repent, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a promiſe of life and ſaluation, he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that hee would haue vs touched to the quicke, and truely ſorie for our faultes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, with firme and ſtedfaſt purpoſe to liue better in time to come: ſo that here wee may knowe what kinde of man he is, which ſhall not periſh, but ſhall haue eternall life, according to this promiſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Zach. Chap. 1. ver. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl> Returne you vnto me ſaith the Lord of hoſts, and J will returne vnto you.</q>
               <p>HEre is an other exhortation to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance ioyned with the promiſe and reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God, very like vnto that before.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Math. Chap. 4. ver. 17.</hi>
                  </bibl> Amend your liues for the kingdome of heauen is at hand.</q>
               <p>THis is the firſt exhortation that the Lord made to the people of Iſrael, agreeable to that where Iohn Baptiſt admoniſheth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:19226:34"/> one to repentance and amendement of life: which that they may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better performe, he addeth this reaſon and promiſe, that the grace of God, the remiſſion of ſinnes, and the reconciliation with God, is preſent and neere to them by the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, which is here called the kingdome of God: for by this meanes the tyranny of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than is deſtroyed and ouerthrowne: the force of ſinne dead: the kingdome of Chriſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly extolled and lift vp on hye, raigning in the hearts of thoſe, which by his ſpirite haue felt the vertue vnto newneſſe of life, a ſufficient token to aſſure vs in this life to be made partakers of his inheritaunce in the life to come.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Math. Chap. 9.13.</hi>
                  </bibl> J am not come to call the rightuous, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to repentaunce.</q>
               <p>THis is the anſwer of our Sauiour made to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phariſies, who finding themſelues offended that he and his companie did eate with Publicanes and Harlots, with ſinfull and leaud liuers, thought him a glutton and loſe fellowe. For theſe men counting them ſelues onely the people of GOD, erred and
<pb facs="tcp:19226:35"/> corrupted themſelues, in ſuch a ſorte, that they accounted all other vtterly profayne. Whereupon our Sauiour Chriſt ſheweth wherefore he leaueth their companies, who ſo much iuſtified themſelues, and betaketh himſelfe and all his to poore ſinners, though they were wicked and euill in life, that by this meanes he might drawe them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their vice and iniquities, and bring them into the right way. To thoſe then, which doe repent of their ſinnes, appertayneth the grace of God, for repentance is the very effect of the ſonne of God, which bringeth ſaluation vnto all people.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 3. ver. 19.</hi>
                  </bibl> Amend your liues therefore and turne, that your ſinnes may be put away.</q>
               <p>THoſe to whom <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake in this place, had put and deliuered to death the holie and the iuſt, the Prince of life, that is to ſay, our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt: yet he exhorteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a godly conuerſation of life, promiſing that their ſinnes ſhall bee forgiuen them, ſo that the grace of God is ſhewed forth to all men, whom the Lorde counteth by putting from them their iniquities.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19226:35"/>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts Chap. 5. ver. 31.</hi>
                  </bibl> This is that Jeſus whome GOD hath lift vp with his right hand to bee a Prince and a Sauiour, to giue repentaunce of ſinnes to Jſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and forgiuenes of ſinnes.</q>
               <p>THis is ſpoken to this ende, that the Lord Ieſus hath brought vs vnto ſaluation by repentaunce, which is neuer ſeperated from the forgiuenes of ſinne.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Cor. Chap. 7. ver. 10.</hi>
                  </bibl> Godly ſorowe cauſeth repentance to ſaluation.</q>
               <p>THe profayne and wicked men continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe reioyce in their wickedneſſe, and harden their harts in their ſinnes, neuer cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing till their accurſed ioye bee turned into weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, by the iuſt and feareful iudgement of God, who caſteth all ſuch into vtter perdition: but they, which haue the feare of God, after that they haue done amiſſe in any ſorte bee greatly ſorie in heart, weeping and lamenting that haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended ſuch a gracious God, and alwaies ſuffer extreme greifes becauſe they offended him, in breaking his commandements. The rulers which had the ouerſight of the church
<pb facs="tcp:19226:36"/> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> beeing reprehended by <hi>S. Paule</hi> for their ſlouthfulnes and ſlownes, in not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitting themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſlaunders, which was reported of them, had for this thing ſuch a diſpleaſure and ſorowe in themſelues, that the Apoſtle thought it commodious &amp; profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for their ſaluation. On which example he draweth this excellent and notable ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that the ſorowe, which is according to the will of God for offending him in neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the charge committed to vs, is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And this is drawne by an vſuall faſhion, to bring the offendor to repentaunce, and to induce a man into an ardent deſire to do bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in tyme to come: which is the way and perfect meanes to come into the porte of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: for ſuch a kinde of repentaunce none ought to bee diſpleaſed, but rather bee glad and reioyce for it.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ioh. 1. Epiſt. Chap. 1. ver. 9.</hi>
                  </bibl> If wee acknowledge our ſinnes, he is faithfull and iuſt to forgiue vs, &amp; to cleanſe vs from all our vnrightuouſneſſe.</q>
               <p>AS the poore ſicke man ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his diſeaſe to the Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to receiue helpe of his griefe: euen
<pb facs="tcp:19226:36"/> ſo ought wee in like maner to acknowledge the ſpirituall deſire of the ſoule before God, not that hee is ignorant of them, or that hee hath neede of any aduertiſement: but to this ende, that we may beare witneſſe of our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull repentaunce and humilitie, which ſhall neuer be without forgiuenes of ſinnes, apprehending the promiſes of God, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallably will fulfill his workes, beeing true and iuſt in all his promiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Prayer.</head>
               <p>THe great and wonderfull bountie of God is ſhewed, when he vouchſafeth to open the heauens vnto vs poore wretched creatures of the earth, making vs fit to enter into his glorious kingdome, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe his eare to heare and vnderſtand our deſires and requeſtes, and exalting the prayers which we make to him in our need, at ſuch tyme as we be moſt poore and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and in greateſt daunger: but the care he hath of vs, and how much he loueth vs is ſeene in this, that hee himſelfe warneth and ſtirreth vs vp, by teaching vs to pray, with aſſurance that he will grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs our requeſts, which he fulfilleth when wee truely require
<pb facs="tcp:19226:37"/> him of his grace, goodneſſe, &amp; mercie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee haue manifould teſtimonies in the word of GOD, which we will ſet downe as worth the noting.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 50. ver. 15.</hi>
                  </bibl> Call vppon me in tyme of trouble, and I will helpe thee, and thou ſhalt honor me.</q>
               <p>ALthough the time when in our ſoules we are afflicted by feeling our ſinne, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be in tribulation or payne, or ſome perrill or daunger: may threaten vs that our God is offended with vs, and will deſtroye vs: yet he promiſeth vs by the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid to deliuer vs from all euill, if ſo wee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor him, and earneſtly deſire in our prayers to haue him our aide, and refuge in our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 145. ver. 18.</hi>
                  </bibl> The Lord is neere to all that call vppon him, yea to all that call vppon him in trueth, he will fulfill the deſire of thoſe that feare him, and will heare their crye and ſaue them.</q>
               <p>ALbeit ſometyme it may ſeeme that God ſhould bee farre from vs, in that he doth
<pb facs="tcp:19226:37"/> not ſo viſibly appeare vnto vs, as he is wont, yet we may be ſure that he is not farre of, if with our whole heart and affection we pray vnto him, if wee bee moued by the feare and reuerence of his name, to obeye him: if wee call vpon him in this ſorte, he will exalt vs, and will deliuer vs from all our ſinnes.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 6. ver. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl> O Lord rebuke me not in thine anger, neither chasten me in thy heauie displeaſure: haue mercie vpon me for I am weake, O Lorde heale me for my bones are bruſed: my ſoule is ſore troubled, but Lorde how long wilt thou delay. Returne O Lorde deliuer my ſoule, ſaue me for thy mercie ſake: for in death there is no remembrance of thee, and in the graue who ſhall praiſe thee.</q>
               <p>FOr as much as Dauid ſayth in the 34. Pſalme, that the eyes of the Lorde are vpon the iuſt, and his eares are readie to heare their mone, in harkening vnto them when they crye, and deliuering them from al their tribulations: and leaſt ſome men might thinke, that poore ſinners are caſt away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, and he wil not vouchſafe to heare their requeſtes, wee heare the Prophet Dauid
<pb facs="tcp:19226:38"/> praying vnto him, not as a iuſt man, but as one feeling himſelfe greatly guiltie of his infirmities, as it is plainly ſhewed in the 38. Pſalm: of the like ſort alſo is it when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth his iniquities to haue ouerwhelmed him, which like a burthen is heauier then he is able to beare: For all this, yet he teſtifieth that although he were poore and miſerable, by reaſon of his ſinnes, yet God had accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his prayers, and taken pitie and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on him.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm. 86. ver. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl> Be mercifull vnto me O Lord, for J crye vnto thee continually, reioyce the ſoule of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, for vnto thee O Lord do I lift vp my head. For thou O Lord art good, mercifull, and of great kindneſſe to all them that call vpon thee.</q>
               <p>DAuid beeing in calamitie, deſired of God to bee reſtored in his ſoule, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the aſſurance of his prayers vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the naturall loue of God, who is by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture gentle, and mercifull, according to his promiſe: yea, he is the very ſelfe ſame foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, vpon which the poore afflicted ought to comfort and reioyce themſelues in heart
<pb facs="tcp:19226:38"/> and ſoule, and by feruent prayer vnto God be deliuered from their iniquities.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ioel Chap. 2. ver. 32.</hi>
                  </bibl> Whoſoeuer calleth vpon the name of the Lord ſhall be ſaued.</q>
               <p>AS faith is neuer without repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, ſo it cannot bee without helpe, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſoueraigne power of God, by calling vpon him according to his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to the ende wee may get his fauour and grace, which is here promiſed vnto vs, as a conſolation and comforte in the greateſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and affliction that we haue: whoſoeuer then of what condition or eſtate he bee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rich or poore, great or ſmall, that doth acknowledge his omnipotent and infinite power, if he humble himſelfe before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and heartely pray him for mercie, let him aſſure himſelfe that he ſhall bee exalted, and that God will be fauourable vnto him.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19226:39"/>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iohn Chap. 16. ver. 23.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erely, verely J ſay vnto you, whatſoeuer you ſhall aske my father in my name he ſhall giue it you, aske and you ſhall receiue, that your ioye may be full.</q>
               <p>THis is the Sonne of God our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt which ſpeaketh, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs certaine that our prayers are exalted: not for our owne worthineſſe, but by his fauour: not by the deſert of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture either in heauen or earth, but in and for his ſake onely, who is our aduocate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. Vpon this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence he doth warne and teach vs to pray vnto his father with this promiſe, that we ſhall neuer bee ſent emptie away, but after this mortalitie hath put on immortalitie, this corruption ſhal put on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption: we ſhall be receiued into ioy and conſolation for euer.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ion 1. Epiſt. Chap. 5. ver. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl> This is the aſſurance that we haue of GOD, that if wee aske any thing according to his will, he will heare vs. And if we know that he heareth vs, whatſoeuer we aske, we know that we ſhal obtaine, that we haue deſired of him.</q>
               <p>WE cannot be in doubt when we come to God in our prayers grounded on
<pb facs="tcp:19226:39"/> his commaundements and promiſe, but that we ſhall be heard and receiue ſuch things as we want, which condemneth thoſe men that call vpon ſtrange Gods: yea, on thoſe which are no Gods, and pray to thoſe which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of this life, who can haue no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of their prayers. But wee muſt bee certaine, that GOD doth hearken vnto vs when wee pray to him, as wee are taught in his holy worde: for he hath promiſed to giue and graunt vs ſuch things as we aſke him, being neceſſary and conformable vnto his will, which are the meanes whereby he vſeth to doe vs good, and to giue vs his grace in full and conuenient tyme.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. Chap. 8. ver. 26.</hi>
                  </bibl> Likewiſe the ſpirite alſo helpeth our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for wee knowe not how to pray as wee ought, but the ſpirite maketh requeſt for vs with ſighings, which cannot bee expreſſed, but he which ſearcheth knoweth what is the meaning of the ſpirite, ſeing he maketh requeſtes for the Saincts according to the will of God.</q>
               <p>AS by the holy Ghoſt wee are lead to the true knowledge of our ſaluation: ſo by it
<pb facs="tcp:19226:40"/> we are made certaine of the ſame, being the ſeale and earneſt of our inheritaunce, which teſtifieth with our Spirite, that wee be the ſonnes of God in that wee hate all euill, and on the contrary take pleaſure in the lawes of the Lord. For it is the Spirit which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth vs in our affliction, and ſtrengthned vs in our weakneſſe, in making vs beare pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently the burden of our tribulation and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities: in ſo much, that our affections be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at variance among themſelues, &amp; many tymes ſlowe to prayer, are yet ſtirred vp by the holy Ghoſt, who teacheth vs to ſtay our ſelues vpon the promiſes, that we are to aſke of God with deſire and earneſt affection of heart, which cannot bee declared in wordes. By this meanes are our prayers exalted to God, and accoumpted iuſt and reaſonable, being made by the holy Ghoſt, which is the Spirite of God, God who acknowledgeth and accepteth that which is his, and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from him by giuing vs deliuerance, and adiudge vs vnto ſaluation. Seing then that our prayers ought to bee ordered according vnto the will of God, and done in ſuch ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and ſinglenes of heart, we may comfort our ſelues in the vertue of his grace, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the holy Ghoſt. To this is added
<pb facs="tcp:19226:40"/> that, which the Apoſtle teacheth in this Chapter, that by the ſpirite of adoption wee may boldly crye abba father. In this maner then ought wee to aſke in faith, and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie without doubting, (as S. Iames exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs) being founded vpon the aſſuraunce, that wee haue of the fatherly goodneſſe of God towards vs, by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Parables, &amp; ſimilitudes of the grace &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God towards poore ſinners, which do repent them ſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is manifeſt not onely by all the ſayinges which heretofore are ſhewed, and other places of holy Scripture to the ſame purpoſe, touching the grace of God proffered vnto vs by the forgiuenes of our ſinnes: but alſo by certaine Parables and Similitudes, which ſerue vs as promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and which our Sauiour Chriſt hath vſed for our comfort: as we may reade in the 15. of S. Luke. The firſt is of the Sheepe that went aſtray, and was loſt in the wildernes, whome the Sheepheard ſeeketh earneſtly, and finding it, taketh it vpon his ſhoulders, bringeth it home, and reioyceth more ouer
<pb facs="tcp:19226:41"/> that one, then for the nintie and nine which he had: in like ſorte (ſaith our Sauiour) is it in Heauen, for one ſinner that repenteth him ſelfe. Hath ſinne then deceiued thee? hath it caried thee away from the flocke of Chriſt, and made thee ſtray from the right path? Art thou in the middeſt of a Deſert, in daunger of a roring Lyon, the enemie to thy ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Withdrawe thy ſelfe betimes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant of thy ſtraying, and goe to thy flocke, leaſt thou periſh vtterly: returne vnto thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Sheepheard Ieſus Chriſt, which will bee gentle vnto thee, neither ſtande in doubt but that he wil receiue thee, if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to him, ſeing he goeth ſeeking and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thoſe which goe aſtraye to bring them into his fould: and when thou art returned be not afrayde, but be ſure of thy ſaluation, and reioyce, for the Angels in heauen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce for thee.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke. Chap. 16. ver. 18.</hi>
                  </bibl> As a woman which hath loſt a peece of ſiluer, after ſhe hath found it againe reioyceth: ſo doth the Angels of God for a ſinner which doth repent.</q>
               <p>ALthough we loſe our ſelues by our owne fault, &amp; bee guiltie of our eſtraying from
<pb facs="tcp:19226:41"/> God: yet for all this he houldeth vs ſo deare and precious, and hath ſuch care of vs, that he will neuer forget vs, but prouideth for our ſaluation, bringeth vs to himſelfe, keepes vs as his owne, euen as though he ſhould keepe ſome excellent treaſure: for which the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall and heauenly Angels doe ſing for ioye and gladneſſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Luke Chap. 15. ver. 11.12.</bibl> BY the goodneſſe of the father towardes his prodigall ſonne, our Sauiour ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the great clemencie of God our celeſtial father towards poore ſinners, which conuert themſelues vnto him.</q>
               <p>If by the lightnes and fooliſhneſſe of our mindes, and by the vanities of our harts we haue abuſed the goodnes of God, either tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally or ſpiritually, &amp; by our owne meanes are drawne from his commaundements in ſlouthfull and diſſolute life, and ſo fallen into confuſion, by feeling our pouertie and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? let vs not feare to turne againe to our God with true humblenes, acknowledging our miſdeedes, ſeeing he is gentle and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, he will receiue vs as his children, he will clothe vs with his benefites and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb facs="tcp:19226:42"/> graces, with all ioye and mirth.</p>
               <p>By the Parable and Similitude of the Publicane, acknowledging himſelf a poore ſinner, ſtanding a farre of, and thinking him ſelfe vnworthie to lift vp his eyes to heauen, ſtriking his breaſtes, and bewayling that he had neglected the mercies of God: our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour makes vs certaine, and perſwades vs of the iuſtification and mercie for our ſinnes, if truely we feele our ſelues guiltie: if we be beaten and humbled in our harts: if we haue a true diſpleaſure, and are ſorie that we haue offended our God: if wee be ſo touched, wee ſhall finde him gentle and quiet towards vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Worthy examples touching the great mercie of God towards poore ſinners.</head>
               <p>ALthough many promiſes and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent proofes be here ſet before vs, as ſufficient to quiet the conſcience of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one: notwithſtanding it ſhall be neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſet forth ſome examples, for more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie and confirmation of the ſame, ſeeing that ſuch examples and inſtructions do ſtirre vs vp the more to conſider better of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Wherefore, as in our firſt father Adam ſinne began to appeare: ſo in him alſo God
<pb facs="tcp:19226:42"/> ſhewed the firſt token of mercie, when he ſaw him loſt and fallen into death, he was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to raiſe him and ſet him vp againe, his clemencie he ſhewed there to be ſo much the greater, and his goodnes declared it ſelfe ſo much openly: for after he had done ſo much good, and ſhewed him ſuch fauour to create him after his own likeneſſe, hauing commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him the ſole authoritie and dominion of all things which are vnder heauen, onely aduertiſing him to obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which he ought in trueth to haue performed: yet among all theſe things ſo eaſie, he lendeth his eares to the craftineſſe of Sathan, rather then to the voyce of his God, and at the length fell into infidelitie and vnthankfulnes towards him: yet he left him not, nor gaue him ouer in ſuch euilles, but goeth after him, although he had deſpiſed and offended him ſo much, neither ſtayeth he till Adam came to ſeeke him: yea, the Lorde goeth firſt to finde him, not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge himſelf, or to chide him by hard repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, as in good right he might doe, but to bring him to the knowledge of his ſinne, and to giue him helpe for his ſaluation. Oh the goodneſſe of God, how marueilous and how wonderfull are his doinges, his mercie is excellent and great: for who knoweth not
<pb facs="tcp:19226:43"/> that where iniquitie aboundeth, there his grace aboundeth much more.</p>
               <p>The ſinne of Lot was no light ſinne in committing inceſt (without thinking on it) with his owne daughters, yet God had mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on him, (as S. Peter teſtifieth) calling him a iuſt man, not in reſpect of the abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable deede, but becauſe of the grace of God which ſhewed it ſelf in him, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt works and godlineſſe, that were in him all his life tyme.</p>
               <p>Iacob hath not bene guiltles, for defiling himſelfe by inceſt with his two wiues being ſiſters: yet God ceaſed not to continue his grace and fauour towardes him, following the promiſe made to his poſteritie for euer.</p>
               <p>The xij. Patriarks the children of Iacob, are accuſed for many diuers great faultes and miſdeedes: as Ruben the firſt borne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed his fathers bed with Bilha one of his Concubines. Iuda did the like with Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar his daughter in lawe, and although he knewe her not, yet he is not excuſed.</p>
               <p>Simeon and Leuy, ſhewed themſelues altogether vnfaithfull, diſloyall, cruell, and bloodie in the murther of the Shechimites. The other brethren mooued with wrath, and fed with hatered, were like murthers on Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph
<pb facs="tcp:19226:43"/> their younger brother, they were ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and without humanitie, that they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to afflict their old father, by making him thinke that ſome wild beaſt had deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his ſonne and their brother Ioſeph: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, for all their miſdeedes, God hath bene mercifull and bleſſed them.</p>
               <p>The ſinne of Aaron is in no wiſe to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, although he had this honour of God to beare his worde with his brother Moſes to the people of Iſrael, and before the King of Egipt, being ordayned an high Prieſt, a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of his Church in the ſeruice was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the lawe: yet he became ſo ſlouthfull of ſo ſmall courage, that he ſuffered himſelfe to bee guided by the affection of the blinde people, ignorant, and ſuperſticious, and not onely conſented to them in their wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprice, but he himſelfe became a workman and founder of their Idoll, and a miniſter to their Idolatrie, ſetting vp the Alter, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynting a feaſt to be ſolemnized for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of their Calfe: for which Moſes his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reproued him very ſharply, as though he had bene onely the cauſe of this euill: for he had by this meanes deſtituted, and diſapoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the people of the grace of God, who was readie to giue them ouer into the handes of
<pb facs="tcp:19226:44"/> their enemies: as we may reade in <hi>Deut.</hi> 9. <hi>Chap. verſ.</hi> 22. Yet his wrath was pacified, neither ceaſed he to continue his goodneſſe towards him, but raiſed and eſtabliſhed him to the office of the high Prieſt.</p>
               <p>It happened alſo that afterward he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a great fault, when he contented not himſelfe with the great office of the high Prieſt, which was graunted him and his ſonnes for euer, but enuied his brother Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, accuſing him as an vſurper, in taking on him the gouernement of the people, for which hee eſteemed himſelfe as worthie as Moſes was. For which cauſe, though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord was angrie againſt him, and his Siſter, and ſtroke them with Leaproſie for the ſpace of ſeauen daies, (a iuſt puniſhment for ſuch a quarrell) yet he vſed ſo great clemencie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, that his wrath went no farther, and healed them.</p>
               <p>After that Dauid had concealed his flight from Saul vnto Abimilecke, and reporting not the trueth, was ſome cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 85 Prieſtes were put to death by the commaundement of Saule, their townes were deſtroyed and ſacked, and all the dwellers therein paſſed on the edge of the ſworde, both men, women and children. Afterward being placed in the
<pb facs="tcp:19226:44"/> Crowne by the ſinguler grace of God, who had deliuered him from ſo many daungers, and made him happely to raigne, and fought ſo many worthie victories, conquering all Gods and his enemies in the lande, made them tributaries to him: yet when the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours fought againſt the Ammonites, and beſieged the Citie of Rabba, the Arke of the Lorde beeing in Campe, he began to liue in eaſe and pleaſure, remayning quietly in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, at which tyme he committed adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie with Bethſabeth, not by the infirmitie of the fleſh, as if had not other meanes to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie his incontinencie, and to quench the heate of his luſt: but by a diſordered deſire, which made him commit whoredome with his Subiects wife: and this alſo made his ſinne much more greeuous, conſidering the tyme wherein he ſhould haue beſtowed him ſelfe in praier for the good eſtate of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the Arke of God: neither was he ſo ſatiſfied, (but cloked ſinne with ſinne) for he cauſed Vrias his faithfull ſubiect to bee murthered by the enemies of God, thereby to couer the ſinne of adulterie: but after hee knewe his ſinne, and God had receiued him to mercie, he repented him of his miſdeedes, and receiued grace and fauour fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:45"/>
               <p>Great and filthie were the ſinnes of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſe the King of Iuda: for he builded vp the high places that his father Ezechias had plucked downe, and worſhipped the Planets as the Sunne, the Moone, and the Starres, and prophaned the walles of the Temple with the Alters that he cauſed to bee built, following al the abhominations of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, he burnt his ſonnes in the fire looking himſelf on them: he receiued Sorcerers, and familiar Spirites: he vſed Witchcraft, and ſet vp grauen Images in the houſe of God, expreſly againſt the commaundement of the Law: neither did he this himſelfe, but cauſed the people alſo to goe aſtray and do the like: and which is more, he reiecteth the attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which was made vnto him and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but gaue himſelfe more and more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euill, and ſold himſelfe altogether to work wickedneſſe in the ſight of the Lord: he ſhed in Ieruſalem much innocent blood, and put to death, thoſe which did reprooue him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not frame themſelues ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his abhominations. For theſe thinges the wrath of GOD was kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, in ſo much that he was ouercome of the Aſſerians, and lead captiue to Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon bound with chaynes: but being there in
<pb facs="tcp:19226:45"/> anguiſh, he humbled himſelfe to God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing that he had beene wicked, cruell, and abhominable: at whoſe complaint God had mercie on him, deliuered him from ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable bondage, cauſed him to returne to Ieruſalem, and ſet him in his kingdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, who beeing thankfull to his God for his goodnes, tooke away the ſtrange Gods, pulled downe the Alters, and eſtabliſhed the pure ſeruice of GOD, with a ſtraight com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to all his people to obſerue it, giuing in this a ful teſtimonie of his true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and conuerſion to God: by this we haue an example, and euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t apparant ſigne of the infinite mercie of GOD towards vs poore and miſerable ſinners, to this end, that none diſpayre in his ſinnes how great and filthie ſoeuer they bee: for (as I haue ſhewed out of Gods word) where ſinne aboundeth, there grace aboundeth much more.</p>
               <p>It was a great and filthie offence, when many of the high Prieſts and Leuites in the tyme of the Captiuitie, and when the wrath of God was ſpred ouer them, and ouer al the people becauſe of their iniquities, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thought on their tranſgreſſions, nor ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for their ſinnes, in turning to the Lord by a true repentaunce, but forgat what he had
<pb facs="tcp:19226:46"/> commaunded them, &amp; tooke ſtrange wiues, lincking themſelues to ſtraunge people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothing their ſonnes and daughters in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and mingling by this meanes the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeede with prophane people, a thing gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally forbidden to all the people of GOD, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.3. but eſpecially prohibited in <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit.</hi> 21.14. Yet when Eſdras a ſoueraigne high Prieſt, a Scribe of the law, a rightuous man vnderſtood this diſorder and confuſion, he was very ſorie, and greatly offended, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king lamentation before GOD for it. The people alſo were taken with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, acknowledging their faultes, and by the commaundement of Eſdras, ſent awaye their ſtrange wiues with their children, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king certaine Offringes in reſpect of their ſinnes, and ſo the bountie and mercifulneſſe of God remayned among them.</p>
               <p>There was a woman ſayth S. Luke in the 7. Chapter of the Goſpell, which was of euill life, who hauing caſt her ſelf at the feete of Ieſus Chriſt weeping, receiued of him ſuch ioye and conſolation, to aſſure her ſelfe that her ſinne was forgiuen her though they were neuer ſo great.</p>
               <p>There was alſo ſayth the ſelfe ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangiliſt in the 19. Chapter, a man called
<pb facs="tcp:19226:46"/> Zacheus, who was a principall Maiſter of the Cuſtome, rich, and of a wicked life: yet when Ieſus promiſed to lodge with him, he ſhewed that hee was come to ſeeke and ſaue that which was lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, by which meanes this poore ſinner was receiued into grace, with a true repentaunce, and goodwill to ſatiſfie againe the hurt which he had done to others.</p>
               <p>I pray you beholde the fall of S. Peter, it is an example to euery one, who being one of the twelue Apoſtles and Doctors of the worlde, brought vp in the knowledge of the Lord, by ſeeing his wonderful myracles, and beeing one of the three witneſſes which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his glorie in the Mountaine, promiſed neuer to forſake him, neither in priſon or in death: yet his infirmitie was ſo great, and ſo fearefull, that he not onely forſooke him, but forſware him three tymes: yet the Lorde in mercie had compaſſion on him, and behelde him though he had made himſelfe vnworthie of the honorable office whereunto he was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned: but repenting &amp; weeping in teares, was one of the firſt which was called vnto his office, and fitted with the giftes of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, to be a ſeruaunt and faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a couragious and valiaunt Martyr of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19226:47"/>
               <p>The vnhappie and wicked man, which for his miſdeeds was hanged on the Croſſe, had his recourſe vnto Ieſus Chriſt in the tyme of death, and was not caſt away but recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into ioye and conſolation, with promiſe, that after his death, not after many yeeres, or ſome ſpace of tyme, or after he had bene in the forged fire of Purgatorie, but preſently whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhould end this mortal life, he ſhould be with Chriſt in Paradiſe.</p>
               <p>He was truely execrable, which was cut of from the number of the faithfull by the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> becauſe againſt all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie and ciuility, he did entertaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the nakedneſſe of his fathers wife: for which cauſe, although he well deſerued to be deliuered to Sathan, excommunicated, and vtterly cut off from the miſticall bodie of Chriſt: yet the Apoſtle S. Paule ſeeing his repentaunce, and vnderſtanding the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the Church had layd vpon him, vſed clemencie &amp; compaſſion, neither would haue the man to ſuffer any greater ſeueritie, but to haue ſome regard in comforting him, for feare hee ſhould bee ſwallowed with too great ſadneſſe. See here what examples the holy Ghoſt ſetteth forth in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as pure &amp; cleare teſtimonies, to proue
<pb facs="tcp:19226:47"/> the great and ineſtimable mercies of God towardes poore ſinners, which doe conuert themſelues with all their harts, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation vnto him, by a true repentaunce and amendement of life. Theſe examples be of ſome force to thoſe whom God hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued lately vnto the communion of his grace, when as he made a way vnto the Gentiles, and called them vnto his Church: All thoſe then, which haue bene before named were of the people of God, &amp; of his houſe: of which, ſome haue ſinned againſt the firſt Table: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers againſt the ſecond: others againſt both by monſtrous miſdeedes: ſome haue robbed: ſome murthered, and done diſſolutly. Some haue committed Adultery, Fornication, and Inceſt. Some Apoſtaties, Idolators, and reuolters from the trueth. Some giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Witchcraft: all they neuertheleſſe haue bene receiued into the mercie of God. O the wonderfull loue of the Lord, how excellent and full of compaſſion is he? Who would not be rauiſhed to beholde his ſtedfaſtneſſe? Who would not truſt in him to reioyce and comforte himſelfe in his mercies? who is a ſtrong hould for the poore afflicted, a refuge for thoſe that be amaſed and deſolate, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to thoſe which are in calamitie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole
<pb facs="tcp:19226:48"/> hope of the poore. It is thou O Lord, which doeſt ſurmount all our iniquities, thou ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweſt them downe, and bringeſt them to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, by acquitting and deliuering vs from them. Is there any then that feeleth himſelf guiltie of any great fault, or any ſinne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted after they haue bin inſtructed in their ſaluation, occupying a place in the Sheepe-fould of the Lord? let him not diſpayre in the clemencie of God, ſeeing he hath here fayre examples before his eyes to followe for his comfort.</p>
               <p>Seeing then it is ſo by ſo many places of holy Scripture, and by the promiſes of God by good examples, liuely exhortations of the grace and mercie of God offered to vs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and ſet foorth by the loue of his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: let vs bee certaine and full aſſured, that if wee beleeue and truely repent, and call vpon him with a true heart and affection, he will bee pacified with vs, what offence ſoeuer wee haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, he will wholly forgiue vs. This is then the conſolation in myne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, for thy word O Lord hath quickened mee. Pſalm. 119.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19226:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
